Guide to the John Pittman Papers TAM.188
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
John Pittman Papers
circa 1880s -1987
1926-1983
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Pittman, John
Pittman, Margrit
TAM.188
6.25 Linear Feet in 6 record cartons and 10 folders in one shared box
John Pittman (1906-1993) was an African-American communist journalist and writer born in Atlanta. He graduated from Morehouse College, and received an M.A. in Economics (1930) from the University of California at Berkeley. In 1931, he founded and served as editor of the San Francisco Spokesman, renamed The Spokesman. Pittman became an editor of the (daily) People's World. Pittman traveled to Europe as a correspondent for the Communist Party's newspapers: Daily Worker (New York), People's World, and for the Chicago Defender. He married fellow communist Margrit Adler and together were Moscow correspondents for the CPUSA press. Pittman was also the founding co-editor of the Daily World in New York. The collection includes biographical materials, correspondence, writings, documentation of his political activities, photographs, graphics, and realia.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Margrit Pittman 1997. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 1997.021, 1997.042, and NPA.2003.039.
Arrangement
The papers are organized into five series:
I. Biographical
II. Correspondence
III. Political Activities
IV. Writings
V. Photographs, Graphics, Realia
Folders are generally arranged alphabetically within each series.
Historical/Biographical Note
John Pittman (1906-1993), an African-American communist journalist, was born in Atlanta, graduated from Morehouse College, and received an M.A. in Economics (1930) from the University of California at Berkeley, with a thesis titled "Railroads and Negro Labor." After a brief stint at Stanford Law School, and jobs as a waiter on the Southern Pacific Railroad and as secretary to art patron Noel Sullivan, in October, 1931 he founded and served as editor of the San Francisco Spokesman (a weekly newspaper for the Bay Area African American community), which by 1934 had been renamed The Spokesman, reflecting Pittman's broader ambitions and leftward political evolution. During that year's San Francisco general strike, he lent The Spokesman's printing presses to the fledgling Communist Party newspaper, the Western Worker, resulting in their destruction by right-wing vigilantes. Then Pittman went to work for the Western Worker, becoming by 1941 the editor of its successor, the (daily) People's World. In this capacity, he was a frequent guest on radio station KSAN (San Francisco) in 1941-1942.
In 1945 he covered the founding conference of the United Nations, and in 1946 received his divorce from his first wife Merle Nance Pittman. In 1947 Pittman traveled to Europe as a correspondent for the Communist Party's newspapers Daily Worker (New York) and People's World, and for the Chicago Defender, a trip made possible by progressive notables including Lena Horne, Paul Jarrico, Albert Maltz, and Dalton Trumbo, whose financial support was coordinated by Los Angeles attorney Leo Gallagher. After his return he married fellow communist Margrit Adler, a German-Jewish antifascist refugee and German-American political activist. They remained in New York until 1955, when they moved to San Francisco with their two children, Carol and John Peter. There Pittman again worked for the People's World. From 1959-1961 the Pittmans were Moscow correspondents for the CPUSA press. In 1968 Pittman came to New York to become the founding co-editor of the Daily World (the result of the merger of the Party's West and East Coast weekly newspapers). In the late 1970s Pittman went to Prague as the Party's representative on the editorial board of the World Marxist Review, returning to New York in 1987. In addition to his newspaper writings, Pittman contributed some two dozen articles to the Party's monthly journal Political Affairs, and wrote Africa Calling, Isolate the Racists: The Liberation Struggle in Southern Africa(1973), and (with Margrit Pittman) Sense and Nonsense About Berlin(1962) and Peaceful Coexistence: Its Theory and Practice in the Soviet Union(1964).
Selected Bibliography (arranged chronologically):
Railroads and Negro Labor. Thesis (M.A. in Economics)--University of California, Berkeley, Dec 1930. 92 leaves.
"A Perspective for Forging Negro-White Unity." Communist 23 (Jan, Feb 1944): 86-91, 174-181.
"The Negro People Spark the Fight for Peace." Political Affairs 25 (Aug 1946): 724-733.
"War on Korea: Point IV in Action." Political Affairs 29 (Aug 1950): 40-50.
"Africa and the United States." Political Affairs 37(Feb 1958): 48-52.
"Books in Review: The Diplomacy of World War II." Political Affairs 37 (Apr 1958): 46-53.
"The October Revolution and National Liberation." Political Affairs 46 (Nov 1967): 27-38.
"Book Reviews: Toward Eradication of Colonialism." Political Affairs 47 (Feb 1968): 90-97.
"Laos: Testing Ground of the Nixon Doctrine." Political Affairs 49 (Oct 1970): 11-19.
"Indochina's 25 Year Struggle Against U.S. Imperialism." Political Affairs 50 (Feb 1971): 1-13.
Africa Calling, Isolate the Racists: The Liberation Struggle in Southern Africa. New York: New Outlook Publishers, 1973. 31 pp.
"Arena of Class Struggle: The United Nations, Part I." Political Affairs 52 (Mar 1973): 18-29.
"Arena of Class Struggle: The United Nations, Part II." Political Affairs 52 (Apr 1973): 31-40.
"A Guiding Ideology for Anti-Racist, Anti-Monopoly Struggle." Political Affairs 52 (Aug 1973) 18-30.
"The United Nations and the Struggle for Détente." Political Affairs 53 (Oct 1974): 44-54.
"Building the Communist Press." Political Affairs 54 (Mar 1975): 24-37.
"What's New in Soviet Agriculture." Political Affairs 54 (Jul 1975): 3-20.
"Book Reviews: A Man of Heroic Mold." Political Affairs 55 (Feb 1976): 54-64.
"The Bonn Congress of the German Communist Party." Political Affairs 55 (Jun 1976): 24-34.
"From Cradle of Bourgeois Freedom to State Monopoly Capitalism." Political Affairs 55 (Jul 1976): 7-9.
"Racism and War." Political Affairs 57 (May 1978): 22-27.
"Afro-American Struggle Today - A Framework." Political Affairs 58 (Feb 1979): 14-22.
"Bulgarian Theoretical Conference: Agreement on Basic Principles." Political Affairs 58 (Mar 1979): 2-7.
"Is Socialism Applicable to the U.S?" Political Affairs 59 (Sep 1980): 12-18.
"Détente: The Only Sane Option." Political Affairs 61 (May 1982): 2-8.
"The Class Role of Affirmative Action." Political Affairs 62 (Mar 1983): 18-24.
"The American Heritage of Karl Marx." Political Affairs 62 (Oct 1983): 15-23.
"Restructuring the World Economy." Political Affairs 64 (Nov 1985): 18-24.
Pittman, John and Margrit.
Sense and Nonsense About Berlin. New York: New Century Publishers, 1962. 60 pp.
Peaceful Coexistence: Its Theory and Practice in the Soviet Union. New York: International Publishers, 1964. 156 pp.
Pittman, Margrit
"The San Francisco Peace Referendum." Political Affairs 47 (1968): 58-63.
"25 Years of the German Democratic Republic." Political Affairs 53 (Oct 1974): 55-62.
"Democracy in Czechoslovakia." Political Affairs 56 (Mar 1977): 13-18.
"Women, Children, Marriage - the Experience of Socialism." Political Affairs 61 (Mar 1982): 10-14.
"Women's Equality in the German Democratic Republic." Political Affairs 66 (Mar 1987): 14-18.
Scope and Content Note
The bulk of the collection is comprised of John Pittman's writings and correspondence. The writings deal with the struggles of African Americans and people of color worldwide, the strategy and tactics of the communist movement and its relationship to the capitalist powers and developing countries; they consist mainly of typescripts, clippings, and photocopies of Pittman's columns and newspaper articles, pamphlets, papers and radio addresses. Correspondence includes letters from family members, friends, U.S. and foreign Communist cadre, and African American journalists, writers, activists, and public figures.
The collection also contains a small amount of biographical and visual materials, as well as materials documenting Pittman's political activities. Biographical materials include documents that pertain to Pittman's mother, Carrie Badger Pittman, and the Badger family, school records, and press credentials; materials on political activities include internal Communist Party documents and some of Pittman's notes on meetings, materials related to a course taught at the Jefferson School of Social Science (an adult education institution of the Communist Party USA located in New York City), and a file of documents relating to the Democratic Party of California in the elections of 1932. Visual materials include photographs--of Pittman, his family and friends-- documenting both personal and professional activities, and a handful of graphics and printing plates for Communist Party publications.
Correspondence.; Journalism -- United States.; Printed ephemera.; Manuscripts for publication.; Legal documents.; Speeches.; Printing plates.; Black-and-white photographs.; Color photographs.; Clippings (information artifacts); Telegrams; African American journalists.; African American press.; Notebooks; Communism -- United States.; African American communists.; Communism |z Great Britain.; Journalism, Communist.; Press, Communist.; African Americans |x History |y 20th century.; Posters.; Yergan, Max, 1892-1975; Randolph, A. Philip (Asa Philip), 1889-1979; Shields, Art, 1888-; Richmond, Al, 1913-1987.; Patterson, William L. (William Lorenzo), 1890-1980; Aptheker, Herbert, 1915-2003.; Jackson, James; Sullivan, Noel; Belfrage, Cedric, 1904-1990.; Wilkerson, Doxey Alphonso, 1905-1993.; Gannett, Betty; Smith, Jessica, 1895-1983; Flory, Ishmael; Gallagher, Leo; Feuchtwanger, Lion, 1884-1958; Field, Frederick V. (Frederick Vanderbilt), 1905-2000; Morehouse College (Atlanta, Ga.); Communist Party of the United States of America; KSAN (Radio station: San Francisco, Calif.); Davis, Benjamin J. (Benjamin Jefferson), 1903-1964; Wilkins, Roy, 1901-1981; Winston, Henry, 1911-1986.; Pittman, John; Hall, Gus; Harrington, Oliver W. (Oliver Wendell), 1912-1995; Herndon, Angelo, 1913-1997; Hughes, Langston, 1902-1967; Allen, Elmer; Jerome, V. J. (Victor Jeremy), 1896-1965; Lochard, Metz T. B., 1896-1984; Mays, Benjamin E. (Benjamin Elijah), 1894-1984; Dennis, Eugene, 1905-1961; Childs, Morris, 1902-1991; Burns, Ben; Bass, Charlotta A., 1880-1969; Pittman, Margrit
- Series I. Biographical
  Scope and Content Note
  This small series (arranged alphabetically) contains a Badger family genealogy, documents relating to Carrie Badger Pittman, school records, phone books, press cards and credentials, invitations, a Paul Robeson autograph, various personal and legal documents (including re his 1945-46 divorce from Merle Nance), ephemera, and memorabilia.
  - Badger, Robert H. (father of Carrie Badger): Last Will & Testament, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical Materials - Chronological, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Biographical Materials - Chronological, 1925-1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Daily World Tribute for John Pittman and Carl Winter, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Family Bible Genealogy, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Invitations, 1931-1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Phone Books (4), undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Pittman, Carrie Badger: Divorce from John Pittman, Sr.; Commitment to New York State Hospital, 1917, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Pittman, John: Divorce from Merle Nance Pittman, 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 8A)
  - Pittman, John: Medical, 1947-1983 (Box 1, Folder 8B)
  - Press Cards and Credentials, 1926-1958 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Robeson, Paul - Autograph, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Robeson, Paul - Program for Concert in Oakland, California, with William Duncan Allen, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 10-A)
  - School Records, 1914-1966 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series II. Correspondence
  Correspondence (most incoming), comprising one quarter of the collection, is organized into two subseries, Chronological (1925-1959) and Alphabetical (bulk 1960-1983) and contains letters from family members, friends (including fellow Morehouse alumni), U.S. and foreign Communist cadre, and African American journalists and activists, including numerous letters received in Pittman's capacity as editor of the Spokesman. Correspondents include the African American communists Marvel Cooke, Ben Davis Jr., Ishmael Flory (a lifelong friend), cartoonist Oliver Harrington, Angelo Herndon, James Jackson, William Patterson, Doxey Wilkerson, and Henry Winston; communists Herbert Aptheker, Phil Bart, Morris Childs, Eugene Dennis, Betty Gannett, Gus Hall, V.J. Jerome, Al Richmond, Art Shields, and Jessica Smith; African American newspaper editor Charlotta A. Bass and Max Yergan, both of the Council on African Affairs; Ben Burns and Metz T.P. Lochard (respectively, editor and publisher) of the Chicago Defender; Pittman's parents Carrie Badger Pittman and John Pittman Sr., cousin Claybert Robinson, and other relatives; friends D.D. Richardson, Mason and Doris Roberson, C.V. Roman, Robert "Red" Saxon, and George A. Towns; letters from Cedric Belfrage, Frederick Vanderbilt Field, Lionel Feuchtwanger, attorneys Leo Gallagher and John T. McTernan, Benjamin E. Mays (President, Morehouse College), A. Philip Randolph, Noel Sullivan, Roy Wilkins; and, from Langston Hughes, a 1934 letter ("Dear Johnny") praising Communist-led unions for not discriminating against Negroes. Note that letters from the highlighted correspondents found in Subseries A (Chronological) may also appear in adjacent and/or other folders within this series.
  - Subseries A: Chronological
    - Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence (Includes letter s from A. Philip Randolph, D.D. Richardson, C.V. Roman (M.D.), Robert "Red" Saxon; various relatives), 1926-1929 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence, ca.1930s (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence (Includes letters from D.D. Richardson, John Pittman Sr., Ishmael Flory), 1930 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence (Includes San Francisco Spokesman), 1931 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence (Includes San Francisco Spokesman), 1932 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence (Includes San Francisco Spokesman), 1933 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence (Includes San Francisco Spokesman; letters from Roy Wilkins & Langston Hughes), 1934 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence (Includes letters from Ben Davis Jr. & A. Philip Randolph), 1935 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence, 1936-1940 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence (Includes letters from V.J. Jerome & Al Richmond), 1942 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence (Includes letters from Angelo Herndon, V.J. Jerome, Eugene Dennis), 1943 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Correspondence (Includes letters from Lion Feuchtwanger, Marvel Cooke, Charlotta Bass, Max Yergan, Art Shields), 1944 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Correspondence (Includes letters from Doxey Wilkerson, Claude Barnett ( Associated Negro Press)), 1945 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence (Includes letters from Morris Childs, William Patterson, John T. McTernan), 1946 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Correspondence (Includes letters from Doxey Wilkerson & Morris Childs), 1947 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Correspondence (Includes letters from Doxey Wilkerson & Charlotta Bass), 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Correspondence (Includes letters from Cedric Belfrage, Charlotta Bass, Karl Nathan (Soviet Anti-Semitism)), Al Richmond, Claybert Robinson, 1950-1955 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Correspondence (Includes letters from Ben Davis, Ishmael Flory, James Jackson, Herbert Aptheker), 1956-1959 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Subseries B: Alphabetical
    - Correspondence - Unidentified, 1971-1983 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence - A, 1962-1983 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence - Aptheker, Herbert and Bettina, 1968-1975 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence - Attorneys, 1953-1956 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence - B, 1964-1983 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence - Bart, Phil, 1974-1978 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence - C, 1965-1979 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence - Chicago Defender(Ben Burns, Metz T.P. Lochard), 1942-1947 (Box 2, Folder 7A)
    - Correspondence - D, 1967-1979 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence- Diskin, Lou, 1973-1977 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence - E, 1964-1983 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence - F, 1964-1982 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence - Field, Frederick, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Flory, Ishmael, ca.1940-1980 (Box 2, Folder 12A)
    - Correspondence - G, 1967-1982 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence - Gannett, Betty ( Political Affairs), 1967-1969 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence - H, 1963-1979 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence - Hall, Gus, 1966-1979 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence - Harrington, Oliver, 1968-1982 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence - Herndon, Angelo, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence - Hughes, Langston, 1934, ca.1953 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence - I, 1968-1981 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence - J, 1969-1983 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence - K, 1965-1978 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence - L, 1968-1983 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Correspondence - Literary Rejections, undated, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Correspondence - Lumer, Hyman, 1963-1976 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence - M, 1963-1982 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Correspondence - Mays, Benjamin E. (President, Morehouse College), 1943-1947 (Box 2, Folder 26A)
    - Correspondence - Meyers, George, 1967-1976 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Correspondence - Morton, Charlie and Goldee, 1967-1977 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Correspondence - N, 1963-1982 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Correspondence - O, 1968-1975 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Correspondence - P, 1967-1982 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Correspondence - Passport, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Correspondence - Pittman, Carol, 1968-1979 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Correspondence: Pittman, Carrie - letters to John Pittman, 1920s-early 1930s (Box 2, Folder 33A)
    - Correspondence - Pittman, Carrie - Death of, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Correspondence - re: Pittman, Carrie, ca.1930-1934, 1950-1954 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Correspondence - Pittman Family, 1968, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Correspondence - Pittman, John Jr., 1968, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Correspondence - Pittman, John Sr., 1930, 1931, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Correspondence - Pittman, Margrit, 1968-1982 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Correspondence - Postcards, 1935-1955 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Correspondence - R, 1963-1979 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Correspondence - Richmond, Al, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Correspondence - Roberson, Mason (Moke) and Doris (Dobby), 1968-1983 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Correspondence -Paul Robeson Archives of (Berlin, East Germany), 1967 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Correspondence - Robinson, Claybert ("Clay") - cousin., 1956, 1970, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Correspondence - S, 1963-1981 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Correspondence - Shields, Art, 1967-1979 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Correspondence - Smith, Jessica ( New World Review), 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Correspondence - Stone, I.F., ca.1940s (Box 2, Folder 48A)
    - Correspondence - T, 1963-1983 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Correspondence - Towns, George Alexander, 1926-1931 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Correspondence - U-V, 1968-1979 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Correspondence - W-Z, 1966-1983 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Correspondence - Winston, Henry, 1969-1983 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Correspondence - Winter, Carl and Family, 1967-1979 (Box 2, Folder 54)
- Series III: Political Activities
  This series (arranged alphabetically, bulk 1960-) contains Communist Party internal documents primarily re: the "Negro Question" (1930s-1980s), notes taken at several 1983 meetings of the Party's Political Bureau, Central Committee, and African-American Commission, a notebook from a 1961 trip to the USSR, materials related to a course taught at the Jefferson School of Social Science, a file of Democratic Party of California documents re the 1932 mobilization of African American voters (Pittman was an advocate of realigning the African American vote from its traditional Republican Party orientation), and clippings and ephemera relating to various events and topics.
  - ABU Membership List [Bay Area Black University students??], undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - African Liberation Struggles Today (Course Outline) - Jefferson School of Social Science, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - The African Peoples and their Struggle for Liberation (Course Evaluation) - Jefferson School of Social Science, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - American - European March, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Asian - African Liberation Struggles (Winter Term Syllabus) - Jefferson School of Social Science, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - China, Trip to - Journal, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - CIO - Texas, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Clipping File - Scheme of Classification, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Communist Party Internal Documents (Negro Question), 1930s-1960s (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Communist Party Internal Documents, 1979-1983 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Communist Party Meeting Notes (Central Committee, Political Bureau, African-American Commission), 1983 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Communist Party - Twenty-first National Convention, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Communist Party of the Soviet Union - Twenty-fifth Congress, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - The Daily World- Job Applications, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Democratic Party of California - Internal Documents re: Mobilization of Negroes, ca.1932 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Hall, Gus, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Hinds, Lennox - Speech by (International Conference of Solidarity with the Struggle of African and Arab Peoples against Imperialism and Reaction), 1978 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - "Hymn to the Rising Sun - A Short Play about an African-American Soldier," by Paul Green, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - International Commission of Inquiry into US Crimes in Indochina, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - International Contacts List, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Jackson, Maurice - Afro-American Peoples Struggles (Seminar - Havana, Cuba), 1981 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Leon, Gilbert (First Lieutenant) vs. United States (Brief Amicus Curiae) - Korean War, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Maran, Rene M. - Interview with, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - May Day: Rallies and Speech, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - McCarran Act Protests Reported in Press, ca.1962 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Murdock, Steve - Death of, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - National Lawyer's Conference, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - National Question - Jefferson School Typescripts, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Nationalities Question - Worldwide, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Negro Candidates for Election on New Party Ticket, undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Negro Press Circulation Figures, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Nikolai Miklukho-Maclay: Fighter Against Racism - By Y.Y. Roginsky, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - North Korea, Trip To, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Philip Alexander Bell and the San Francisco Elevator, By John H. Telfer (San Francisco Negro and Cultural Society, California History Series, Monograph # 9), 1966 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Pittman, John and Margarit - List of Articles Approved for The Daily Worker and People's World, 1959-1962 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Pittman, John - Work Record of (1974-1979), undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Pittman's Books - Prague to New York, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Polan, Lou: Statement Before the House Un-American Activities Committee, undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Prague / World Marxist Review- Activities, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 39)